Inventory to the Records of the Equal Rights Amendment Campaign Archives Project (ERACAP) (1970-1985)
Sophia Smith Collection
Interview and discussion with Beth McAllister at the NC ERA office in 1979, one week before the first vote of the year on the ERA in the NC Senate. Individuals appearing include Beth McAllister, her administrative assistant Basil Burn, and Jessie Rae Scott. They discuss the philosophy behind the opposition, the anti-ERA campaign in general, and address issues concerning many voters in the NC House and Senate. Other topics covered include homosexual marriage, discrimination against the elderly, social security, fundamentalist churches and ministries, fundraising, the John Birch Society, and ERA as a legal versus social issue.
#29, "Marilyn at home, beginning, n.d."
Marilyn DeVries and her husband are interviewed at home. Topics include the structure of the family, the legality of the ERA, Sam Ervin, the media, the potential harms and dangers of the ERA, Gloria Steinem/Betty Freidan and the "Humanist Manifesto," the National Gay and Lesbian Taskforce, Henderson v. Henderson, humanism vs. Christianity, and the breakdown of moral standards due to homosexuals, feminists, and the ERA movement, etc.
#30, "Craig Lawling [Lawing] interview (#24), n.d."
Continuing footage showing Beth McAllister, Senator Craig Lawing, Senator Rachel Gray, and others, discussing Lawing's support of the ERA. Topics include Jessie Rae Scott, Lawing's philosophy on the ERA and the evolution of his ideas, political strategies concerning the passage of the ERA, killing the bill in committee, etc. Footage then shows a group of pro-ERA supporters (including Beth McAllister) waiting for the results of a legislative vote.
#31, "ERA Rally, crowd shots, 2 anti ERA interviews, 1979"
Assistant news director Mike Kozel of a local NC news station conducts interviews with crowd members outside of the North Carolina State Legislature building at an ERA rally in early 1979. Particular focus is on anti-ERA representatives from Fayetteville and Cumberland county and NC church groups. Interviewees discuss women's rights and the ERA, the constitutionality of ERA, abortion and infanticide, and single-issue church groups.
#32, "WPJL radio show continued (#21), n.d."
*DVD may not work in DVD player or Mac computer.
Part two of the WPJL radio call-in show with Marilyn DeVries and Alice Winn Gatsis. Issues discussed are retirement and the ERA, abortion, Henderson v. Henderson, humanist philosophy, marriage and marriage complications, women's roles, and ERA's constitutionality.
#33, "Interview with Betty in office pt 1 (#22), 1979"
Beth McAllister, Basil Burns, Senator Rachel Gray, and others are filmed in the office. Beth McAllister discusses her role in the pro-ERA movement. Other discussion topics include anti-ERA rhetoric, Beth's upcoming debate against Alice Winn Gatsis, homosexual marriages, the John Birch Society, Jesse Helms, Beth's family, her personal views on the ERA, and her credentials/career history.
#34, "Beth McAllister and Kim Spencer questioning Cockerham, n.d."
North Carolina General Assembly, winter 1979. Beth McAllister, George Miller, and Jack Stevens discuss the possibility of ERA ratification. Senator Walter C. Cockerham holds a press conference in which he announces that he has conducted a poll in his district and the results are not in favor of the ERA. Beth McAllister asks him if he will release his poll results so that they can be CPA-certified, but he refuses. Beth McAllister is then herself interviewed by members of the press. Finally, Beth McAllister and Senator Rachel Gray discuss the possibility of Senator William Craig Lawing killing the ERA bill in committee.
#35, "WPJL radio show, beginning (#20), n.d."
First part of 1979 WPJL footage (1 of 3). Marilyn DeVries and Alice Winn Gatsis on the North Carolina Christian radio station, WPJL ("We Proclaim Jesus Lord"). They introduce themselves and their views on the ERA. Marilyn DeVries declares that the ERA is "overkill," and Alice Winn Gatsis argues that God made men and women different, therefore the ERA will create societal chaos. DeVries and Gatsis answer questions from callers, both pro- and anti-ERA. Other topics include Senator Sam Ervin's arguments against the ERA, and the effects of the ERA on homosexuality as a legal institution, abortion, pornography, and the draft.
#36, "Interview with Beth in office (#18), 1979"
*DVD stops playing after approximately 14 minutes.
North Carolina ERA headquarters, 1979. Basil Burns, Beth McAllister's administrative assistant, discusses the pro-ERA reactions to the Marilyn DeVries and Alice Winn Gatsis WPJL radio show. Burns refutes their claims that homosexual marriages were allowed in Colorado as a result of the ERA. Beth McAllister then contemplates the differences between the philosophies of the pro- and anti-ERA leaders, while Basil Burns suggests that for the majority of anti-ERA followers, it is merely a question of an "information gap." Other issues discussed include the construction of the family and the anti-ERA's position on the Biblical family model.
#37, "Radio show on abortion, pt. 2 (7), n.d."
Continuation of #35: Second part of 1979 WPJL footage (2 of 3). Marilyn DeVries and Alice Winn Gatsis continue their discussion by questioning the meaning of "sex" in the text of the ERA bill. They also explain that ERA proponents are secular humanists and atheists who support abortions on demand and "homosexual resolutions" at last year's 25-Point National Plan of Action. They mention that Gloria Steinem wants to overthrow the Biblical patriarchy. DeVries and Gatsis answer questions from callers, and DeVries argues that the ERA will make homosexuality seem normal (by allowing homosexual marriage and homosexuals to adopt), but that it is, and always will be, "sick." DeVries calls the ERA "anti-God, anti-family [and] phony."
#38, "Who will protect the family, Hickory shoot, Pat @ LWV meeting #1-3, 1981"
First part of the League of Women Voters gathering, Catawba County, North Carolina. Pat Blackstone and other members of the LWV discuss various issues, such as the freedom of choice vs. right to life and NC Senator Jesse Helms' attempt to remove family planning options from foreign aid. Blackstone and a group of older women talk about the ERA and its relationship to divorce, retirement, widowhood, Social Security, the wage gap (women earn $.59 to a man's $1.00), spousal abuse/domestic violence.
#39, "Who will protect the family, Hickory shoot, Pat @ LWV meeting, Tape #2, 1981
*DVD stops playing after approximately 20 minutes.
Second part of the LWV gathering footage (2 of 3). Pat Blackstone and the group of LWV discuss the Commission on the Status of Women; the need for a rape crisis center in Catawba County; and women's universal need for love, worth, and a feeling of importance. Another topic discussed is the need for factory women to have good daycare for their children and adequate wages to pay for it. Pat Blackstone mentions that the American Bar Association had estimated that it would take 475 years to eliminate all of the discriminatory laws against women in the United States.
#40, "Who will protect the family, Hickory shoot, Pat @ LWV meeting, Tape #3, 1981
*DVD stops playing after approximately 13 minutes.
Third part of the LWV gathering footage (3 of 3). Pat Blackstone and the group discuss the philosophy of anti-ERA women and give their answers to the question, "who will protect the family?" At the end, Pat gives an informal speech to the LWV on their support of the ERA, the desire to halt the building of an oil refinery off the North Carolina Coast due to the possible negative environmental effects, and how to deal with the upcoming budget cuts.
#41, "Factory, lunch discussion, Hickory, #7, 1981"
Pat Blackstone asks female North Carolinian Ridgeview Mills factory workers why men get paid more than women even though they do the same jobs that are equally difficult. Other topics include the need for daycare at the factory and a discussion in response to the question, "who will protect the family?"
#42, "Factory #5, 1981"
Some of the women from #41 working in the Ridgeview Mills hosiery factory. They talk about how long they've worked there, opinions on the ERA, their "life stories."
#43, "Pat and family discussion at dinner #12, n.d."
Pat Blackstone with her husband and two children at their home. Pat tells the story of "Phyllis," a rape victim whose rapist was acquitted because of Phyllis' "lifestyle." The family is recorded at dinner, discussing the children's schooldays. After dinner, Pat and her husband are questioned about their marriage. Pat's husband discusses his opinions as a mental health professional and describes "families in transition."
#44, "Chris Settle #11, n.d."
*DVD stops playing after approximately 16 minutes.
Pat Blackstone talks to her hair stylist while she gets her hair cut at the salon. The footage then cuts to a 1981 Catholic high school graduation. Senior Chris Settle gives a speech.
#45, "Settle Yard, Poovey, George and Mary Morris #14"
Continuing footage of post-graduation ceremonies. Footage then shifts to a conversation with Representative George Poovey, George and Mary Morris, Reverend and Mrs. Settle, and others, discussing the pro-family movement and the reasons for "breakdown of the family," such as women working outside of the home. Other topics include childcare and the separation of church and state.
#46, "Interview with Hugh Gaither, Hickory, 1981"
An interview with Hugh Gaither, the Financial Officer of the Ridgeview Mills hosiery factory in Catawba County. He discusses the mill's payment methods/compensation philosophy, management/employee relations, his views on providing on-site daycare, and his support of the ERA (influenced by his mother's opinions).
#47, "Phyllis rape story #9, Hickory, 1981"
DVD begins with more footage of Ridgeview Mills factory workers, then switches to Pat Blackstone at her hair salon. Her hair stylist, Phyllis, discusses her "life story:" marriage, divorce, children, her career, single parenting, etc.
#48, "Phyllis rape story #10, 1981"
Continuing footage of Pat Blackstone's conversation with Phyllis. Discussion topics include myths about the ERA, hostile reactions/threats Pat has received, and women in opposition to the ERA. Then, Phyllis begins to discuss her rape trial and her rapist's subsequent acquittal. Phyllis describes her polygraph test, her treatment by the prosecution in the courtroom, and the little support she received from the District Attorney's office.
#49, "Unidentified #13, n.d."
Continuing footage of the 1981 Catholic high school graduation ceremony, including the commencement speech, songs, the distribution of diplomas, a prayer, and the end of the ceremony.
#50, "Settle Yard #15, NC Hickory, 1981"
Continuing footage of the conversation with Representative George Poovey, George and Mary Morris, Reverend and Mrs. Settle, and others. Topics include secular humanism, "misguided" liberals, public schools vs. Christian schools, education in the home, problems with the welfare system, and domestic violence/the breakdown of the family structure.
#51, "Settle Yard #16, NC Hickory, 1981"
Continuing footage of the conversation with Representative George Poovey, George and Mary Morris, Reverend and Mrs. Settle, and others. Reverend Settle discusses how secular humanism has undermined the values of the home, and men feel frustrated because they are no longer the head of the household, which has led to an increase in domestic violence. Therefore, domestic violence will stop once wives become submissive to their husbands. Mary and George Morris discuss their marital dynamics and how they have improved since Mary abandoned feminism for Christianity and complete submission to George. Representative Poovey talks about the problems with the ERA and states that "men and women are not equal." Members of the groups then answer the question, "who will protect the family?"
#52, "ERA hearing, Sam Ervin's speech, 1979"
A Joint House and Senate hearing on the ERA. Begins with introductions, rules, etc., then Senator Sam Ervin gives an anti-ERA speech in which he argues that the ERA is unnecessary and unconstitutional.
#53, "ERA-NC tape 5, Beth Ch. 1, Shotgun Ch. 2, n.d."
Footage of the filmmaker's sister describing her struggle with drug abuse/addiction, beginning as a teenager and continuing into her adulthood.
#54, "NC Hickory #8, 1981"
More footage of a female worker in the Ridgeview Mills hosiery factory. Discussion topics include a typical work day/routine, low wages/wage disparities, and social issues.
#55, "Factory, interview, begin lunch scene, 1981"
Continuing footage of the Ridgeview Mills hosiery factory. Factory workers talk to Pat Blackstone about their life experiences, political opinions, and views on the ERA.
#56, "Unidentified 17, 1981"
*Sound stops working at 19 minutes.
Continuing footage of the conversation with Representative George Poovey, George and Mary Morris, Reverend and Mrs. Settle, and others. Topics include religion vs. the state, "who will protect the family?" (God), approval of President Reagan's current presidency, liberalism, welfare, etc.
#57, "Fitzgerald conservatives #1, 1981"
Group of "North Carolinians Against ERA" conservatives discuss topics such as the specific language of the ERA bill, homosexual adoptions, gay/lesbian movement, Reverend Mooneyham, moral majority, welfare, the women's movement, rising divorce rate, etc.
#58, "Fitzgerald conservatives #2, 1981"
Continuing footage of the interview with "North Carolinians Against ERA." They discuss the definition of "the family," abortion, the history of the women's movement, opposition to Betty Friedan and Gloria Steinem, gender roles, support of the "Protect the Family" Act, etc.
#59, "Fitzgerald conservatives #3. 1981"
Continuing footage of interview with "North Carolinians Against ERA," with the addition of Representative Poovey. They discuss the abolishment of the Status of Women Commissions, the ERA, state-funded abortions, and the "New Generation" Act. Other topics include pro-life legislation/ideology, and Representative Poovey says he believes "every mother should have to view the remains of her aborted child."
#60, "Pat B at church #21, 1981"
Pat Blackstone explains the ERA (on behalf of the League of Women Votes) to an adult church group. She also gives a brief history of the women's rights movement and how it relates to the ERA and gives statistics about women in the workforce (nationally and within North Carolina), women's property rights and child custody/child support, etc.
#61, "Pat B at church #22, 1981"
Continuing footage of Pat Blackstone explaining the ERA to a church group. Pat answers questions from, and debates with, members of the audience (mostly men). Topics include judicial interpretations, gender roles within the military, the draft, etc.
#62, "Pat B at church #23, 1981"
Continuing footage of Pat Blackstone explaining the ERA to a church group. Topics include the military, domestic violence/rape, Phyllis Schlafly, etc. Footage then shifts to various outdoor shots.
#63, "Settle's Christian graduation, #20"
More footage of Chris Settle's graduation from his Christian high school (Tabernacle Christian School). Footage includes a speech from the president of the senior class, and speeches from eight other graduating seniors (not including Chris Settle).
#64, "Settle teens and town CA's #18, n.d."
Chris Settle and Jamie, the valedictorian, discuss their views on the ERA, abortion, humanism, their plans for the future and personal philosophies/principles, and women's roles in society. Footage then shifts to various outdoor shots of Hickory, North Carolina.
#65, "NC Hickory #19, 1981"
Pat Blackstone talks in her kitchen while she cooks dinner. She discusses her background/upbringing, why she became involved with the ERA, her reactions to her visit to the Ridgeview Mills hosiery factory, grassroots organizing, her relationship to the League of Women Voters of Catawba County (President), and begins talking about her friend Phyllis.
#66, "Pat B at home and cutaways"
Pat Blackstone and her husband Paul talk in their home about the family, women in the workplace, federally funded social services (and upcoming cutbacks), Paul's personal views on the ERA, and Pat and Paul answer the question "who will protect the family?"
#67, "Family Raleigh #4"
*DVD may experience technical difficulties.
Continuing footage of "North Carolinians Against ERA" being repositioned in various poses. Footage then shifts to Senator Craig Lawing answering questions about his support for the ERA, his predictions for the future of the ERA, Senator Helms, pro- vs. anti-ERA movements, etc.
#68, "Fitzgerald - Beth Raliegh [Raleigh] #10, 1981"
Beth McAllister discusses Marilyn DeVries, her life experiences/upbringing, her ERA opponents, the civil rights/women's movements, the politics surrounding the bill, the history of the ERA in North Carolina, the political tactics/attitudes of ERA supporters, Pat Blackstone, the low economic status of women in North Carolina (56% of women in the workforce). Other topics include abortion, affirmative action, the history of segregation, homosexuality, the New Right, and misinformation about the ERA.
#69, "Fitzgerald - Miriam, Beth, Raliegh [Raleigh] #7, 1981"
Beth McAllister and Miriam Dorsey, the director of the North Carolina Council on the Status of Women (NCCSW), discuss the need for the protections of the ERA against the Reagan administration and cultural changes. Miriam also explains her role as the director of the NCCSW. Beth and Frances Fitzgerald talk about various topics. Beth introduces herself as the North Carolina ERA coordinator, the president of the North Carolinian Junior League for ERA, and a wife and mother. Beth also describes her personal history and her reasons for becoming involved in the pro-ERA movement, her education, and her similarities/differences to Marilyn DeVries.
#70, "Fitzgerald - Miriam, Beth Raliegh [Raleigh] #8, 1981"
Continuing footage of Beth McAllister and Miriam Dorsey. Dorsey discusses the priorities of the North Carolina Council on the Status of Women, such as the ERA, equitable distribution of property, and state funding for abortions for low-income women. She also talks about the changing roles of men and women in society, the women's movement, the need for increasing support and assistance for sexual abuse victims, the Family Protection Act, the current political climate (state and national), the need for more government-funded social services, and legislative support for the ERA.
#71, "Fitzgerald - Raliegh [Raleigh] #6, 1981"
Senator Rachel Gray and Representative Louise Brennan answer questions about the history of the ERA in the North Carolinian General Assembly, their hopes for the future of the ERA, the current conservative/"authoritarian" political climate of national politics, and the budget.
#72, "Fitzgerald - Raliegh [Raleigh] #7, 1981"
Footage of film crew member Frances Fitzgerald asking questions/creating additional footage to be added to her interview with Alice Winn Gatsis.
#73, "Lamarr's [Lamar's] church/sermon #20, 1981"
Reverend Lamar Mooneyham gives a sermon at his church, the "Tri-City Baptist Temple" on Father's Day. The sermon is directed at fatherhood, and Mooneyham leads his congregation in the singing of various hymns. Footage then shifts to an interview with Mooneyham. He discusses his political participation with the moral majority/local grassroots movement, textbooks and the faults of the public school system, the presentation of "life as it ought to be" rather than "life as it is" to schoolchildren, and anti-pornography and anti-obscenity legislation, and sex education.
#74, "Lamarr's [Lamar] church/sermon #21, 1981"
Continuing footage of Reverend Mooneyham's sermon, addressed particularly to men and "how God evaluates the man." The Bible is described as the ultimate authority in describing roles of men, women and the family. Mooneyham cites that, at present, the divorce rate of 55% has negative effects on the nation (politically, socially, and economically). ERA is perceived as a by-product of the "failures of husbands and fathers."
#75, "Lamarr's [Lamar] Church/sermon #22, 1981"
Continuing footage of Reverend Mooneyham's sermon on the roles of men and women. He discusses the meaning of marriage in relation to God/the Bible, presented, against a backdrop of high divorce rates and dissolving families. According to this interpretation of the Bible, God can fix all familial problems. After the sermon, church members are shown talking to Mooneyham. One of the discussion topics concerns starting church daycare, as per Senate-supported legislation.
#76, "Lamarr's [Lamar] Church/sermon #23, 1981"
Continuing footage of Reverend Mooneyham's interview, where he answers the question, "who will protect the family?" ("Families will protect families"). Footage then shifts to Frances Fitzgerald and Miriam Dorsey talking to a small group of women about the North Carolinian domestic violence program.
#77, "Family - Raleigh #13, 1981"
Frances Fitzgerald interviews Marilyn DeVries. Discussion topics include the history of the anti-ERA campaign, the nuclear family, her involvement with Alice Winn Gatsis and Senator Helms, the NOW book "Revolution: Tomorrow is NOW," the religious-based forefathers of the United States, and her religious and personal background.
#78, "Fitzgerald-Family - Raleigh #14, 1981"
Continuing footage of the Marilyn DeVries interview. She discusses the "women's lib movement" in contrast to her ideas about the home and the church, her opinion that receiving the Lord has nothing to do with ERA, the economic crisis, and women working outside of the home. She asserts that it is important to spend time with children and family and to teach family values and morals, not work outside of the home.
#79, "Fitzgerald--Family - Raleigh #15, 1981"
Continuing footage of the Marilyn DeVries interview. She answers the questions, "who are you?" and "who will protect the family?" Other discussion topics include daycare centers as a government control and the fundamentalist Christian concerns about Christ-centered ethics being removed from schools. She also discusses "reverse discrimination" and affirmative action as well as racial justice as a moral value. Other topics include the equitable distribution of property bill, "alternate lifestyles," domestic violence, and the "liberal sentiment" of newspapers and the media.
#80, "Family - Raleigh, #16, 1981"
Continuing footage of the Marilyn DeVries interview. Frances Fitzgerald poses various questions but footage does not include Marilyn's answers.
#81, "Family - Raleigh #19, 1981"
Shots of African-American children at a playground and then of African-American families at a park, and then African-American families at a park. The second half of the DVD shows Reverend Mooneyham's congregation singing hymns.
#82, "Battered women shelter, #24, 1981"
Frances Fitzgerald and Miriam Dorsey interview a group of women at a domestic violence shelter in North Carolina. Topics include their children, experiences with law enforcement, responses to the notion that battered women can overcome spousal abuse if they are more submissive to their husbands, reasons that men abuse their wives, the cycle of violence, and answer the question, "who will protect the family?"
#83, "Fitzgerald Beth reverses #12, 1981"
Footage of Frances Fitzgerald posing questions to add to earlier footage of her interview of Beth McAllister.
#84, "Family--Fitzgerald - Beth #11, 1981"